An Inventory of the European Pictorial Collection
Hoover Institution Archives
European Pictorial Collection
1918-2001
XX772
4 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes, 1 slide box, 37 envelopes, 1 oversize folder, 1 album box (6.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Photographs, postcards, and slides, depicting cities, prominent personalities, and historical events in various European countries, particularly in Eastern Europe. Includes scenes of the Hungarian Revolution of 1918-1919; the coup of 1926 in Poland; the revolt of 1934 in Austria; post-World War II communist activities in Romania; and the Solidarność movement in Poland in the 1980s.
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open for research
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in Stanford University's online catalog.
Subjects
NSZZ "Solidarność" (Labor organization); Austria--History--1918-1938--Pictorial works.; Europe--Pictorial works.; Hungary--History--Revolution, 1918-1919--Pictorial works.; Poland--History--Coup d'état, 1926--Pictorial works.; Romania--History--1944-1989--Pictorial works.; Poland--History--1980-1989--Pictorial works.
Container List
- 16 prints of scenes of street fighting and destruction during the Austrian revolt of 1934; 10 postcards of personalities involved; 5 postcards of views of Melk in der Wachau, Austria. (File A)
- 1 print of the Czech opera singer Otakar Marak, 1919, autographed. (File B)
- 3 prints and 4 negatives depicting the invasion of Czechoslovakia by Soviet troops, August 1968; 1 negative of Premier Dubcek; 1 negative of a view of Prag. (File C)
- 23 prints depicting daily life in the small town of Zagora, Greece, under the Junta's rule. (File D)
- 1 pictorial booklet depicting buildings, bridges and monuments in Budapest, Hungary. Captions in German and Hungarian. (File E)
- 16 prints depicting scenes from the Hungarian Revolution of 1918-1919; 31 postcards of leaders of the Hungarian Soviet Republic; 8 photocopies of posters from the Hungarian Revolution 1 illustrated newspaper section of leaders of the Hungarian Soviet Republic. (File mF)
- 1 print of Nicholas Horthy, regent of Hungary, 1920-1944, with a dedication to the Hungarian peasantry signed by Horthy, November 16, 1919. (File G)
- 1 print of Eamonn De Valera, President of Ireland, 1959-1973. (File mH)
- 1 post card of Benito Mussolini, Italian Fascist premier, 1922-1945. (File I)
- 1 print of crowd in Northern Italy demonstrating in favor of occupation and annexation by Yugoslavia, 1948. (File J)
- 20 prints depicting various places of interest in Wilno, Lithuania, 1920's; and 6 prints, 1992. (File K)
- 32 prints depicting street fighting in Warsaw, Poland, at the time of Marshal Pilsudski's coup in May 1926. (File L)
- 1 print of Generalissimo Francisco Franco, ruler of Spain, 1939-1975. (File m*M)
- 12 prints depicting various locations in Yugoslavia. (File Q)
- 1 print depicting the unveiling in Poznan, Poland, of a statue of President Woodrow Wilson, in 1931. (File R)
- 44 prints and 2 postcards depicting Budapest and the Hungarian countryside and people, 1931. (File S)
- 2 prints an 8 postcards depicting various monuments in Basel, Vienna, Heidelberg, as well as a performance of "die walkure" in Bayreuth, 1931. (File T)
- 4 prints of Republican supporters (women, Carlist youth, and Communists involved in the destruction of churches) in Spain, 1936. (File U)
- 5 prints depicting street scenes and demonstrations in Czechoslovakia in 1990. (File V)
- 12 prints depicting scenes from the Hungarian Revolution of 1956. (File W)
- 4 prints of President Vaclav Havel of Czechoslovakia, and 1 postcard of Hradcany Square, 1989-1992. (File X)
- 7 prints and postcards of the history museum Brama Stracen Cytadeli in Warsaw, Poland, 1992. (File Y)
- 30 prints of political demonstrations in Czechoslovakia, 1989, and of election campaign posters in Slovakia, 1992. (File Z)
- 1 album of prints of a Lithuanian literary exhibition in Moscow and scenes of cultural activity in Estonia and Latvia, 1948; and 7 prints and accompanying booklet of scenes in Romania following the revolution of 1990. (Box 1)
- Prints, 1970-1987, of Polish dissidents, gatherings and scenes associated with the Solidarnosc movement, the Polish priest Jerzy Popieuszko and his funeral, and visits of Pope John Paul II to Poland. (Box 2-3)
- 9 postcards depicting Latvian government buildings, government leaders and military parades, 1938; and 5 prints of Baltic independence demonstrations and Latvian monuments, 1988-1990. (File AA)
- 28 prints of Nicolae Ceausescu, other Romanian communist leaders, and scenes of Romanian communist activities, ca. 1947-1985. (File AB)
- 31 prints of Nicolae Ceausescu and his wife with various world leaders, ca. 1960s-1980s. (File AC)
- 76 prints of Romanian communist demonstrations, ca. 1980s. (File AD)
- 51 color photographs of election posters in Slovakia, 1994. (File AE)
- 15 prints of street-fighting in Poland, 1970. (File AF)
- 16 prints of political prisoners in Poland, ca. 1980s. (File AG)
- 30 prints of underground printing presses in Poland, CA. 1980s (File AH)
- 11 prints of the visit of Pope John Paul II to Poland, 1983. (File AI)
- 48 prints of the Polish priest Jerzy Popieluszko and of his funeral, 1984. (File AJ)
- 72 prints of Polish dissidents, and of gatherings and scenes associated with the Solidarnosc movement, ca. 1980s. (File AK)
- 1 print of the transfer of the ashes of Ignacy Paderewski to Warsaw, 1992. (File AL)
- 1 album of prints depicting the life and career of the Bulgarian communist leader Todor Zhivkov (File fAM)
- 1 album of prints of the inspection of a Polish army mechanized division by the Polish communist leader Edward Gierek, 1971. (Box 4)
- 13 prints of Lech Walesa and other delegates at the opening session of the Polish Sejm, 1989. (Box 3)
- Slides of Italian election posters, 1994-1996. (Box 5)
- Prints of visits of Fidel Castro, Nikita Khrushchev, Jerzy Kosinski and Richard M. Nixon to Poland, 1963-1989. (Box 3)
- Prints of Polish political and military leaders, 1965-1975. (Box 3)
- Negatives of election poster billboards in the Czech Republic, 1996. (Box 3)
- Postcards of Polish armed forces, n.d. (Box 3)
- Postcards of war damage in Dubrovnik, 1995 (Box 3)
- Photographs of election posters in Bosnia, 1996. (Box 3)
- Photographs of the visit of the Polish Cardinal Szczepan Wesoly to the United States, 1997. (Box 3)
- Slides of the reinterment of the body of General Wladyslaw Sikorski in Krakow, 1993. Postcards of Pope John Paul II, 1997. (Box 3)
- Autographed photograph of President Guntis Ulmanis of Latvia, 1997. (Box 3)
- Filmstrip depicting social conditions in interwar Poland (Box 3)
- Prints of Poles in Germany, ca. 1930s. (Box 6)
  Photographs of Edith Stein memorial in Poland, 1997. Photographs of Prague, 1990. Photographs of Tirana, Albania, 1996. Photographs of the Romanian royal family, ca. 1990s. Negatives of election posters in Poland, 1997. Postcards of Wroclaw Poland, n.d. Prints of the painting of religious pictures in Ol'shanskii Church, Prague, 1942.
- Prints and photographs depicting social condition in Poland, Czechoslovakia and Estonia, ca. 1930s. Prints of anti-communist demonstrations in Prague, 1989. Prints of Grand Duchess Charlotte of Luxembourg, 1939-1942. Prints of election campaigning in Bosnia and Herzegovina, 1996. Prints of President Boleslaw Bierut of Poland and F.L. Belin, American ambassador to Poland, 1933-1947. (Box 6)
- Photographs of Skwer Hoovera in Warsaw, 1998. (Box 6)
  Photographs of election posters in the Czech Republic, 1998. Photographs of election posters in Slovakia, 1998. Photographs of President Emil Constantinescu of Romania, 1998. Photographs of social and political conditions in Albania, 1985-1999.
- Photographs of the Austrian socialist Friedrich Adler, n.d. Photograph of Prime Minister Jerzy Buzek of Poland, n.d. Photograph of leaders of the Osterreichische Volkspartei, 1999. (Box 7)